Guide to the Zimbabwe Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Zimbabwe collection
1893-2010
MS 1551
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
14.02
(19 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, printed material, and photographs relating to the history of Zimbabwe and current political, economic, and social conditions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator. Transferred from the Zeta Collection, Mudd Library, 2004.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
African Collection, MS 605; Pamphlet Collection, MS 1351; African Postcard Collection, MS 1575. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The material in the original accession is arranged chronologically, with scrapbooks and photographs last. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, printed material, and photographs relating to the history of Zimbabwe and current political, economic, and social conditions.
Children -- Zimbabwe; Education -- Zimbabwe; Housing -- Zimbabwe; Women -- Zimbabwe; Zimbabwe -- Description and travel; Zimbabwe -- Economic conditions; Zimbabwe -- History -- Chimurenga War, 1966-1980; Zimbabwe -- Politics and government; Zimbabwe -- Social conditions; Photographs -- Zimbabwe
- Inventory
  - Jeary, Joseph E.: letterbook of a trip from England to Salisbury, Rhodesia, 1898-1899 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificate of special registration of a claim on the Shamrock South Gold Reef, Gwelo District, 1901 March 30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Rhodesian Railways: Locomotives and General Working"; (see also FOLIO), 1927, 1930s, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Southern Rhodesia: general information booklets; government statements, newsletters, pamphlets, 1943, 1958-1960, 1964, 1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Preliminary Results of the Census of Population," Southern Rhodesia, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Colour Bar in the Copper Belt, by Julius Lewin, South African Committee on Industrial Relations, South African Institute on Race Relations, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Native Welfare Bulletin": publication of the Federation of Native Welfare Societies in Southern Rhodesia, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "African Welfare Bulletin": publication of the Federation of African Welfare Societies in Southern Rhodesia, 1946-1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Liberal Party: statement of native policy, [1947?] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fabian Society: booklets, flyers, 1951, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Fragments of writings on the Wankie Game Reserve, [post 1952] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Nyasaland: demands for secession, 1953, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Arts/crafts: theater programs, catalogs, 1953, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Partnership in Practice in Central Africa," The African Development Trust, [1955?] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Newspapers, 1955-1961, 1966, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Capricorn Africa Society: articles, reports, letters, statements, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Interracial Association of Southern Rhodesia: memoranda, newsletters, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Africans of Nkana, a brochure about the workers of Rhokana Corporation, [1957?] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Federation of Rhodesia and Nayasaland: papers on, interviews, reports, 1957-1962, 1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 19 - 20)
  - The Africa Bureau: booklets on Central Africa and Rhodesia, 1957-1968 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Southern Rhodesia African National Congress: photocopies of documents, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - College of Rhodesian citizenship Association: addresses, minutes of meetings, booklets, 1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Rhodesian Institute of African Affairs: newsletters, informational booklets, 1958-1968 (Box 2, Folder 24 - 25)
  - Academic/educational journals, papers, printed materials, 1958-1964, 1970-1975, 1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - United Federal Party: pamphlets, newspapers, 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - My Trip to the Rhodesias Central Africa, by Francis A. Ibiam, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Planning the Development of the Wealth of Three Nations: An Examination of Economic Possibilities in the Rhodesias and Nyasaland After the Mouckton Report, by The Phoenix Group, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - How Government Works, by P. A. C. Laundy, Southern Rhodesia African Literature Bureau, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "Central Africa Intelligence Report": publication of African Newspapers, Ltd., 1962 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - "Intimidation in Central Africa: Vote for Me...Or Else," East Africa and Rhodesia Publishers, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Office of Southern Rhodesia Affairs, British Embassy (Wash., D.C.): reports, newsletters, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - The Office of Rhodesian Affairs, British Embassy (Wash., D.C.): reports, newsletters, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Rhodesia Ministry of Information, Immigration and Tourism: general information booklets, political pamphlets, printed materials, addresses, other related materials, 1965-1970, 1976, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Government of Rhodesia: proclamations, pamphlets, booklets, 1965-1979 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - "Report from Rhodesia," the Fact Finding Mission of the American-African Affairs Association, [1965?] (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Immigration papers, Rhodesia, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Letters of J. W. Waddell of Rhodesia to Barbara and Lawrence Gorden of South AFrica, 1966, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Anglo-Rhodesian Society: booklets, letters, newsletters, 1966, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - "Press Comment on Rhodesia": publication of Rhodesian Information Office (Wash., D.C.), 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Rhodesian Information Office (Wash., D.C.): press statements, addresses, pamphlets, 1966-1969, 1974-1977, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - "Rhodesian Viewpoint": publication of the Rhodesian Information Office (Wash., D.C.), 1966-1970 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - "Rhodesian Viewpoint": publication of the Rhodesian Information Office (Wash., D.C.), 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 44 - 45)
  - The Manica Trading Company, by W. V. Brelsford, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - "Congressional Record: Proceedings and Debates," United States of America, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Zimbabwe United People's Organization (ZUPO): manifesto, constitutions, statements of principles, 1971-1979, undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Rhodesian Air Force: newsletters, programs, printed materials, 1972-1980, undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - "You and your future in Rhodesia," The Rhodesian Front, [1973?] (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - "Rhodesia: South Africa's Sixth Province," by John Sprack, International Defense and Aid Fund, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - "Report": a newsletter published by The Rhodesia Party, 1974-1976 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Central African Building Society (CABS): annual report, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - News magazines, 1975, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - "Focus on Rhodesia": successor to "Rhodesian Commentary"; prepared by the Rhodesian Information Office (Wash., D.C.), published by the Rhodesian Ministry of Information, Immigration, and Tourism, 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 55 - 56)
  - Candour League of Rhodesia: newsletter, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Sithole, Ndabaningi: letter to Zimbabweans regarding the history of the Zimbabwe African National Union (ZANU); additional printed materials, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Rhodesia Christian Group and other Christian organizations: newsletters, pamphlets, programs, 1976-1982, undated (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Organization of African Unity (OAU): declarations, addresses, [1976?], 1989 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - "Save Rhodesia Campaign" and other related organizations: brochures, pamphlets, printed materials, 1977, undated (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Economics/commerce: surveys, newsletters, directories, reports, 1977-1983, 1988-1993 (Box 5, Folder 62 - 63)
  - "Silver Jubilee Celebrations" program, The Rhodesiana Society, 1978 May (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - United National Liberals: statement about launching of the party, 1978 October (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Zimbabwe-Rhodesia, the Transitional Government: pamphlets, statements, printed materials, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - United African National Council (U.A.N.C.): manifestos, briefings, election materials, 1979, undated (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Zimbabwe African National Union (ZANU): constitutions, press statements, election materials, 1978-1986, undated (Box 5, Folder 68 - 69)
  - "Circular to Zimbabweans": Zimbabwe Democratic Party (ZDP), 1979 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - United National Federal Party (U.N.F.P.): manifestos, booklets, election materials, newsletters, 1979, undated (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Government of Zimbabwe: statements, addresses, reports, 1980-1989 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Zimbabwe Ministry of Information: magazines, pamphlets, printed materials, 1980-1989 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - The Chamber of Mines of Zimbabwe: addresses, booklets, reports, 1982, 1988-1990 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs: newsletters, 1982, 1989, 1992-1994 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Zimbabwe: general information pamphlets; brochures; booklets, 1982-1989, undated (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Britain-Zimbabwe Society: newsletters, addresses, printed materials, 1984-1994, undated (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - "Notes on a Visit to Zimbabwe," Africa Centre, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - "Child Survival and Development," UNICEF, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Independent Zimbabwe Group (IZG): election flyer, [1985?] (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Labor/unions: news magazines, newspapers, writings, 1985-1986, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - "Oxfam America News": newsletter on Mozambican refugees in Zimbabwe, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - "The One Party State": address to One Party State meeting by Didymus Mutasa, 1986 July 19 (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - "Zimbabwe Today": speech by unidentified speaker, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - "Rhodesia to Zimbabwe: Negotiations that Worked," by David McDowell, New Zealand Permanent Representative to the United Nations, 1986 April 19 (Box 6, Folder 85)
  - Amnesty International: update, 1986 July (Box 6, Folder 86)
  - "An Assessment of the Likely Effects of S. A. Retaliatory Economic Sanctions Upon (a) Countries in the Region (b) Zimbabwe," by Zdenek Silarecky, standard Chartered Bank, 1986 September (Box 6, Folder 87)
  - Women's organizations: booklets, reports, and related materials, 1986-1993, undated (Box 6, Folder 88)
  - Mugabe, Robert and Sarah, President and First Lady: informational booklets, 1987-1991 (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - Student publications, University of Zimbabwe, 1988-1992 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - Legal Resources Foundation (LRF): pamphlets, 1988, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Organization of Rural Associations for Progress (ORAP): pamphlet, [1990?] (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Southern Africa Chronicle: newsletter of Africa Information Afrique (AIA), 1990 April 3 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - "Anthrax Epizootic in Zimbabwe, 1978-1980: Due to Deliberate Spread?," by Meryl Nass, M.D., Physicians for Social Responsibility, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - South African Development Community: booklets, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Matabeleland Zambezi Water Project (MZWP): informational flyers, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Conservative Alliance Zimbabwe: message from I. Dougals Smith, undated (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Constitution Party: statement of aims, undated (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - "Rhodesia: An Independent Presentation of the Facts," by Gerald Sparrow, undated (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Zimcare Trust for the Care and Education of the Intellectually Handicapped: statement of objectives, undated (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - "Follow On": a Rhodesian song composed by Ethel Redgate, words by Hylda Richards, undated (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - The Sunday News, Bulawayo: scrapbooks of column entitled "Mainly About People, Places and Events," by "Sandra", 1936-1938 (Box 7)
  - Photograph album [compiled by officer in the British South Africa Police]; includes photographs of Zanzibar, Kenya, Egypt, and England, 1927-1931 (Box 8)
  - Photographs of Salisbury by "Hans", 1952 (Box 8)
  - Photographs by A. Weston Jarvis, Circa 1896 (Box 9)
  - Landscape photographs (Box 10)
- Additional Material, Accession 1995-M-210
  - Additional printed materials, 1900-1997, undated (Box 1)
  - Additional printed materials, 1900-1997, undated (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-042
  - Additional printed materials, 1915, 1950-1952, 1960-1968, 1977, 1990-1997, undated (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Accession 2004-M-052
  - Academic freedom [statement by Association of University Teachers], [1989?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "The Africans' Predicament in Rhodesia" [report no. 8, Minority Rights Group], 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anglo-Rhodesian relations/settlement proposals [British Commission on Rhodesian Opinion, Rhodesian government reports, Canadian Intelligence Service, speech by Joshua Nkomo], 1966-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Declaration of Independence from the United Kingdom [copies from Ministry of Information], 1965 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Development and tourism [policy brief by Zimbabwe Environmental Research Organization (ZERO)], 2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Constitutional Assembly [flyers, newspaper, journal], 2000, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Rhodesian flag [version used from 1968 to 1980] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Smith, Ian [official government Christmas card from Prime Minister and Mrs. Smith], [1970-?] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "This is Rhodesia" [reports on economy and development from Rhodesia Information Service], 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Vox Populi: Township Theatre News" [vol. 1, no. 3], 1992 December (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Erinnerungen an unsere Reise in Mashonaland" [photograph album of travels in Zimbabwe], 1893 May 27-July 6 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Additional Material, 1947, n.d; Accession 2005-M-078
  Scope and Contents
  The accession contains oversized photographs of Southern Rhodesia. Some of the photographs document a visit by the British royal family in 1947 and include images of King George VI, Queen Elizabeth, and Princesses Elizabeth and Margaret. The prints show the royals inspecting the troops, relaxing with dignitaries, attending various functions, and visiting famous sites, such as the grave of Cecil Rhodes and Victoria Falls. The majority of the photographs, however, depict the landscape of Southern Rhodesia under colonialism, including images of natives, colonists, and various buildings and monuments. The accession also contains photograph descriptions, which match the order of the photographs. The images and descriptions appear to have been produced by the public relations department of Southern Rhodesia.
  - Royal visit to Southern Rhodesia
    - Photograph descriptions for box 1, undated (Box 1)
    - Photographs, 1947, undated (Box 1)
  - Landscape of Southern Rhodesia
    - Photograph descriptions for box 2, undated (Box 2)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 2006-M-014
  - "The African Home News," vol. 12, 1965 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chapungu Sculpture Park newsletter, vol.1, no. 1, 1992 December (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cultural Exchanges, bulletin of the Alliance Française", 1984 August (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Grassroots Book News", 1992 October (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Insider, no. 1, 1990 December-1991 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mjosa Humor, no. 1, 1984 July-September (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - MS - Zimba, magazine of the MS-Zimbabwe NGO, no. 1, 1991 March (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - UDI press pack, Rhodesia, 1965 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Womens Action Group Newsletter, no. 2, 1984 November (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Zpra Combat Diary 1976," Zpra is the military wing of ZAPU (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Additional Material, 1894-1998; Accession 2010-M-079
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged as received.
  - Printed material
    - The "Transformation of Men to Meat" Story, Native Affairs Department information sheet, 1960 November (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Notes on the Manners and Customs of the Winamwanga Wiwa," by James A. Chisholm (loose pages), 1908 February (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Banyama, 1937, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Banyama or Bafyeka refers to mythical vampire men.
    - Synopsis about "Mukapi", 1959 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "The Rhodesian Way of Life," by Vernon Brelsford, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Extracts From Report By Commissioner Johnson Of The First Three Years Of Administration Of The Eastern Portion Of British Central Africa", 1894 March 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Voyage Au Zambese, " by Paul Guyot, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "S.S. Liemba," by Col. L. B. Cane, 1947 June (Box 1, Folder 1)
      S.S. Liemba was a flagship of the German flotilla during World War I.
    - "The Turning Point," Zimbabwe African People's Union (ZAPU), 1979 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The Sunday Mirror (PLC): Balance Sheet and Relative Accounts, 1963 March 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "The Student Forum," vol. 2, no. 3, National Union of Rhodesian Students, 1965 April (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Reality: Voice of the Central African Party," no. 3, 1961 January 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Vision, S. Rhodesia (Rhodes Centenary Exhibition Number), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Central Africa Intelligence Report (Southern Rhodesia), vol. 11, no. 11, 1963 November (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The African Pilot (2 issues), 1965 September-October (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Newsfront, no. 23, 1964 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Poverty Reduction Forum: Annual Report, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Zimbabwe Progress Report 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Third annual progress report produced by UNICEF advocating children's rights.
    - Nhume Isithunya - Messenger, vol. 5, no. 2 (magazine for Southern Rhodesia government field workers), 1962 August (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - The Rhodesian, vol. 1, no. 8 (official organ of the Dominion Party), 1958 October (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Rhodesian Mercury, 1965 November 4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Electra, 1968 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
      A compilation of poetry by various authors.
    - Tribal Areas of Rhodesia Research Foundation: Annual Report, 1973, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The Seiler Report: Southern Rhodesia Issues in American Politics," no. 1, 1980 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Rhodesian Crisis, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      An account of the Rhodesian crisis compiled by the editorial staff of Africa Research Limited.
    - Rhodesian Crisis, Supplement No. 1, 1964 January- 1965 October (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photograph, stereoscopic, of bridge on the Cape-to-Cairo Railway over the Zambezi River, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Published by the Keystone View Company.
- Additional Material, 1897-2010; Accession 2015-M-001; 2.02
  - Printed material, 1897, 1953-2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Poster, Circa 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)